8 steps to protect your Cisco router 
Daniel B. Cid 
daniel@underlinux.com.br 
Network security is a completely changing area; new devices like IDS (Intrusion 
Detection systems), IPS (Intrusion Prevention systems), and Honeypots are modifying the 
way people think about security. Companies are spending thousand of dollars on new 
security devices, but forgetting the basic, the first line of defense: the border router. 
Although a lot of people may think that routers don’t need to be protect, they are 
completely wrong. A lot of secure problems appear all time against this kind of device 
and most of them are vulnerable. 
Some information about some common security problems found on Cisco Routers, can 
be read on the text “Exploiting Cisco Routers”, available at: 
http://www.securityfocus.com/infocus/1734
 
In this article I will give you 8 steps, easy to follow, to minimize your Cisco router 
exposure by turning off some unused services, applying some access control and 
applying some security options available on that. 
1- Control Access to your router; 
2- Restrict telnet access to it; 
3- Block Spoof/Malicious packets; 
4- Restrict SNMP; 
5- Encrypt all passwords; 
6- Disable all unused services; 
7- Add some security options; 
8- Log everything; 
1- Control Access to your router
The first thing to do is apply some rules to restrict all external access to some ports of the 
router. You can block all ports, but it is not always necessary. These commands bellow 
will protect your router against some reconnaissance attacks and, obviously, will restrict 
access to these ports: 
access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 7 
access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 9 
access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 13 access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 19 
access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 23 
access-list 110 deny tcp any host $yourRouterIP eq 79 
int x0/0 
access-group in 110 
Where $yourRouterIP is your router IP and x0/0 is your external interface. We 
Will always use this convention in this article.
2- Restrict telnet access to it 
Telnet is not a very safe protocol to use, but if you really need to use it (you should 
always use ssh) you might want to restrict all access to it (remember that all your traffic 
will be unencrypted). The best way to accomplish that is using a standard access-list and 
the access-class command. 
access-list 50 permit 192.168.1.1 
 access-list 50 deny any log 
 line vty 0 4 
 access-class 50 in 
 exec-timeout 5 0 
Where 192.168.1.1 is the IP address allowed to telnet the router 
3- Block Spoof/Malicious packets 
You must never allow loopback/reserved IP address from the Internet reach your external 
interface and you can reject broadcast and multicast addresses too. 
access-list 111 deny ip 127.0.0.0 0.255.255.255 any 
access-list 111 deny ip 192.168.0.0 0.0.0.255 any 
access-list 111 deny ip 172.16.0.0 0.0.255.255 any 
access-list 111 deny ip 10.0.0.0 0.255.255.255 any 
access-list 111 deny ip host 0.0.0.0 any 
access-list 111 deny ip 224.0.0.0 31.255.255.255 any 
access-list 111 deny icmp any any redirect 
int x0/0 
access-group in 111 
4- Restrict SNMP SNMP must always be restrict, unless you want some malicious person getting a lot of 
information from your network ☺
access-list 112 deny udp any any eq snmp 
 access-list 112 permit ip any any 
 interface x0/0 
 access-group 112 in 
And if you are not going to use SNMP at all, disable it: 
no snmp-server 
5- Encrypt all passwords
A very important thing to do is protect all your passwords using the powerful algorithm 
as possible. 
The password from exec mode, that grants privileged access to the IOS system, 
Can be set using a MD5 hash, which is the strongest option available on the 
Cisco IOS. 
enable secret $yourpassword 
All other passwords, you can encrypt using the Vigenere cipher that is not 
Very strong, but can help. To do that, you can use the service password-encryption
Command that encrypts all passwords present in you system. 
service password-encryption 
6- Disable all unused services
 6.1 - Disable Echo, Chargen and discard
 no service tcp-small-servers 
 no service udp-small-servers
 6.2 - Disable finger
 
 no service finger 
 6.3 - Disable the httpd interface no ip http server 
 
 6.4 - Disable ntp (if you are not using it)
 ntp disable 
7- Add some security options
 7.1 - Disable source routing
 no ip source-route 
 7.2 - Disable Proxy Arp
 
 no ip proxy-arp 
 7.3 - Disable ICMP redirects
 interface s0/0 (your external interface) 
 no ip redirects 
 7.4 - Disable Multicast route Caching
 interface s0/0 (your external interface) 
 no ip mroute-cache
 6.5 - Disable CDP
 no cdp run 
 6.6 - Disable direct broadcast (protect against Smurf attacks) 
 no ip directed-broadcast 
8- Log everything
To finish, you must log everything on an outside Log Server. You must everything from 
all your systems and always analyze the logs. 
logging trap debugging 
 logging 192.168.1.10 where 192.168.1.10 is the ip of your log server (configured as a Syslog server) 
Conclusion 
With these simple steps you can add a lot of security to your router, protecting it against a 
lot of possible attacks, increasing your network security. 
Only as an example, you can see the nmap result before and after applying these options: 
Before: 
bash-2.05b# nmap -O 192.168.1.1 
Starting nmap V. 3.00 ( www.insecure.org/nmap/ ) 
Interesting ports on (192.168.1.1): 
Port State Service 
7/tcp open echo 
9/tcp open discard 
13/tcp open daytime 
19/tcp open chargen 
23/tcp open telnet 
79/tcp open finger 
80/tcp open http 
Remote OS guesses: AS5200, Cisco 2501/5260/5300 terminal server IOS 11.3.6(T1), 
Cisco IOS 11.3 - 12.0(11) 
After: 
bash-2.05b# nmap -P0 -O 192.168.1.1 
Starting nmap V. 3.00 ( www.insecure.org/nmap/ ) 
Warning: OS detection will be MUCH less reliable because we did not find at least 1 
open and 1 closed TCP port 
All 1601 scanned ports on (192.168.1.1) are: filtered 
Too many fingerprints match this host for me to give an accurate OS guess 
Nmap run completed -- 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 403 seconds